<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>BrainOverfl0w</title>
    <description>Frederic Jacobs&apos; Personal Blog</description>
    <link>https://www.fredericjacobs.com/blog/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://www.fredericjacobs.com/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jun 2023 12:02:38 +0200</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 22 Jun 2023 12:02:38 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.2.2</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Real World Crypto 2022 - Exposure Notifications Private Analytics</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I was delighted to be presenting at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://rwc.iacr.org/2022/program.php&quot;&gt;Real World Crypto 2022 conference&lt;/a&gt; in Amsterdam on Exposure Notifications Private Analytics. It’s exciting to see large scale deployments of multi-party computation and that such systems are &lt;a href=&quot;https://datatracker.ietf.org/wg/ppm/about/&quot;&gt;on-track to be standardized&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/realworldcrypto?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#realworldcrypto&lt;/a&gt; and now we have &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/FredericJacobs?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@FredericJacobs&lt;/a&gt; on stage telling us about exposure notification and privacy! &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/zl3uxr0wxY&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/zl3uxr0wxY&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Yolan Romailler (@AnomalRoil) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/AnomalRoil/status/1514231604696264708?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;April 13, 2022&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Really nice to see such Apple &amp;lt;~&amp;gt; Google collaboration with such a focus on user privacy 🙏 Great talk, and it&amp;#39;s even cooler to have public whitepapers and all around it.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Yolan Romailler (@AnomalRoil) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/AnomalRoil/status/1514238776125579266?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;April 13, 2022&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;The approach of &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/Apple?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#Apple&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/Google?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#Google&lt;/a&gt;, “Exposure Notifications Private Analytics” is neat, simple and elegant.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;and the deployment insights regarding MPC was so valuable (see pictures).&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;So many challenges were introduced, startup ideas?&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/realworldcrypto?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#realworldcrypto&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/3dU0mA1smL&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/3dU0mA1smL&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Emad Heydari Beni (@heydari_be) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/heydari_be/status/1514238308678840332?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;April 13, 2022&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 13 Apr 2022 01:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.fredericjacobs.com/blog/2022/04/13/EN-Private-Analytics/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.fredericjacobs.com/blog/2022/04/13/EN-Private-Analytics/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Presenting at WWDC - Introducing CryptoKit</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I was happy to present at WWDC this year. You can find &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.apple.com/videos/play/wwdc2019/709/&quot;&gt;the video on developer.apple.com&lt;/a&gt;, or in the WWDC app. It was a pleasure to introduce a fast, easy-to-use and secure cryptographic (as in cryptography!) library for Swift.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2019 01:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.fredericjacobs.com/blog/2019/08/01/introducing-cryptokit/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.fredericjacobs.com/blog/2019/08/01/introducing-cryptokit/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>On the &quot;WhatsApp backdoor&quot;, Trade-Offs and Opportunistic Authentication</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A week ago, The Guardian broke an “exclusive” story titled &lt;a href=&quot;http://web.archive.org/web/20170113123010/https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2017/jan/13/whatsapp-backdoor-allows-snooping-on-encrypted-messages&quot;&gt;“WhatsApp backdoor allows snooping on encrypted messages”&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-reporting&quot;&gt;The Reporting&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first reaction when I skimmed through the story is that this was nothing new . The Guardian’s source had already blogged about it on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://tobi.rocks/2016/04/whats-app-retransmission-vulnerability/&quot;&gt;16th of April&lt;/a&gt; and given &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/VmgfXkVQwpc?t=2903&quot;&gt;a lightning talk at CCC&lt;/a&gt; explaining the issue. Other people in the security community had already looked into this behavior too. Running the story as “exclusive” and sending a push notification to all subscribers as if it were breaking time-sensitive news, while this was known in the security community for months, seems disingenuous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other issue I had with the reporting of this story was the framing that this was a backdoor. This claim has been debunked by now, not matching the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zdziarski.com/blog/?p=6077&quot;&gt;technical definition of a backdoor&lt;/a&gt;. The Guardian ended up &lt;a href=&quot;http://web.archive.org/web/20170120044416/https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2017/jan/13/whatsapp-backdoor-allows-snooping-on-encrypted-messages&quot;&gt;rephrasing their headline&lt;/a&gt; to reflect that this was not a backdoor. While they did change that important categorization, they left the reaction and analysis from the people who commented on the story, largely unchanged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Original:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Professor Kirstie Ball, co-director and founder of the Centre for Research into Information, Surveillance and Privacy, called the existence of a &lt;strong&gt;backdoor&lt;/strong&gt; within WhatsApp’s encryption “a gold mine for security agencies” and “a huge betrayal of user trust”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After adjusting headline:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Professor Kirstie Ball, co-director and founder of the Centre for Research into Information, Surveillance and Privacy, called the existence of a &lt;strong&gt;vulnerability&lt;/strong&gt; within WhatsApp’s encryption “a gold mine for security agencies” and “a huge betrayal of user trust”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I do agree that a backdoor would have been a huge betrayal of user trust, I do not agree that this particular issue was a betrayal of user trust. Unlike with a backdoor, subvert purposes are improbable and the edited story should have reflected that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-trade-off&quot;&gt;The Trade-Off&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Message encryption is maturing as a field and has some pretty elegant solutions deployed in “the real world”, “usable authentication” is still an open problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;WhatsApp is known for being &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.erlang-factory.com/upload/presentations/558/efsf2012-whatsapp-scaling.pdf&quot;&gt;very reliable&lt;/a&gt; and their users love them for that. They decided that unread messages, should be retransmitted upon a change of phone number, matching the behavior they had before adopting end-to-end encryption or any “cloud-based” messenger. Instead of losing the messages that were sent and never read, WhatsApp will automatically retransmit them to the recipient’s new phone, without letting the sender verify the new “security code” first. Since &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fredericjacobs.com/blog/2016/04/29/more-on-sms-logins/&quot;&gt;phone networks, that are used for authentication by mobile messaging apps, are insecure&lt;/a&gt; or WhatsApp servers could get hacked, this leads to some practical attacks that would lead to the compromise of a streak of unread messages upon retransmission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can agree that this was a reasonable trade-off to make in the name of reliability. But such security trade-offs are nothing new, and they are important. When Signal came around, many praised it for adopting a TOFU (Trust On First Use) model. Most “secure messaging” clients up to then, the biggest one being OTR, had been bugging users about fingerprint verification, significantly hurting the adoption of end-to-end encryption. With Signal’s TOFU model, keys are implicitly trusted on the first use. Peers may then confirm that trust by verify their keys through an out-of-band channel. That’s a potential security risk. Does that make Signal backdoored or inherently insecure? No. It was a trade-off that made people actually use end-to-end encryption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can definitely discuss the merits of such trade-offs but dismissing them as backdoors will just drive people away to unencrypted or opportunistically encrypted solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;WhatsApp transitioned from plaintext to opportunistic encryption to all the messages, from over a billion people, being encrypted by default. Then, once that was complete, enabled the phase we are currently in of “&lt;strong&gt;opportunistic authentication&lt;/strong&gt;” until we find a scalable solution to the authentication problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Organizations like &lt;a href=&quot;https://simplysecure.org&quot;&gt;SimplySecure&lt;/a&gt;, or mailing lists such as Trevor Perrin’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://moderncrypto.org/mailman/listinfo/messaging&quot;&gt;Secure Messaging mailing&lt;/a&gt; lists, promote great ideas for tackling these issues. Let’s keep things moving forward to a place where we can all confidently say that we have “encrypted and authenticated communications” by default.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;further-readings&quot;&gt;Further readings&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://tonyarcieri.com/key-rotation-user-experience-crypto-reporting&quot;&gt;Key rotation, user experience, and crypto reporting&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2017/01/google-launches-key-transparency-while-tradeoff-whatsapp-called-backdoor&quot;&gt;Google Launches Key Transparency While a Trade-Off in WhatsApp Is Called a Backdoor&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 20 Jan 2017 14:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.fredericjacobs.com/blog/2017/01/20/whatsapp-backdoor-copy/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.fredericjacobs.com/blog/2017/01/20/whatsapp-backdoor-copy/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>check.torproject.org &amp; IPv6</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;TLDR&lt;/em&gt;: Exit nodes with IPv6 addresses connect to check.torproject.org over IPv6, causing the IP not to be recognised as being one of an exit node. This triggers a scary “Sorry. You are not using Tor.” warning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When firing up &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.torproject.org/projects/torbrowser.html.en&quot;&gt;Tor Browser&lt;/a&gt; today and checking if the browser was properly using Tor, I got the following scary message.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/img/tor/ipv6TorCheck.png&quot; alt=&quot;Scary IPv6 Tor Check&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-i-assume-happened&quot;&gt;What I assume happened&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Confused, I quickly checked if that was my IPv6 address. Thankfully it wasn’t. Tor browser was correctly proxying traffic over the Tor network but the exit node resolved &lt;a href=&quot;check.torproject.org&quot;&gt;check.torproject.org&lt;/a&gt; over IPv6. A DNS lookup for &lt;a href=&quot;check.torproject.org&quot;&gt;check.torproject.org&lt;/a&gt; gives:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;~ ❯❯❯ host check.torproject.org
check.torproject.org is an alias for chiwui.torproject.org.
chiwui.torproject.org has address 138.201.14.212
chiwui.torproject.org has IPv6 address 2a01:4f8:172:1b46::abba:20:1
chiwui.torproject.org mail is handled by 10 eugeni.torproject.org.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What likely happened is that the exit node connected to &lt;a href=&quot;check.torproject.org&quot;&gt;check.torproject.org&lt;/a&gt; over IPv6. Since Tor doesn’t have full support for IPv6 yet, the exit node appeared as unknown, hence triggering this warning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;quick-fix&quot;&gt;Quick fix&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the warnings are scary and we shouldn’t be telling users to just ignore them. A quick easy fix would be to simply not have any IPv6 DNS records in &lt;a href=&quot;check.torproject.org&quot;&gt;check.torproject.org&lt;/a&gt; as long as IPv6 isn’t fully supported.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any thoughts or suggestions? Discuss on &lt;a href=&quot;https://lists.torproject.org/pipermail/tor-dev/2016-August/011304.html&quot;&gt;Tor-Dev&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Update (24th of August)&lt;/em&gt;: The AAAA record &lt;a href=&quot;https://trac.torproject.org/projects/tor/ticket/19940&quot;&gt;was removed&lt;/a&gt;, waiting for a more broader IPv6 support in Tor.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 18 Aug 2016 07:30:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.fredericjacobs.com/blog/2016/08/18/torcheck-ipv6/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.fredericjacobs.com/blog/2016/08/18/torcheck-ipv6/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>On SMS Logins II : an example from Telegram in Russia</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A few months ago, I wrote &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2016/01/14/sms-login/&quot;&gt;a post on SMS logins&lt;/a&gt; following a wave of attacks attempting to take over Iranian Telegram accounts. Recently, there have been new confirmed cases of attacks in both &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Ammir/status/725754152677195777&quot;&gt;Iran&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/kozlovsky/posts/10208948934790884&quot;&gt;Russia&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/kozlovsky_en&quot;&gt;Oleg Kozlovsky&lt;/a&gt; is an opposition activist and the director of Vision of Tomorrow Center in Moscow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/kozlovsky/posts/10208948934790884&quot;&gt;Facebook post written in Russian&lt;/a&gt;, he explains how his Telegram account got hacked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/plugins/post.php?href=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.facebook.com%2Fkozlovsky%2Fposts%2F10208948934790884&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;762&quot; style=&quot;border:none;overflow:hidden&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowtransparency=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At 2:25 AM MSK on Friday April 29th, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MTS_(network_provider)&quot;&gt;MTS&lt;/a&gt; (Russia’s largest mobile operator), disables SMS service on his phone number. After 15 minutes of disconnection, someone tries to log into Oleg’s Telegram account. The process for authorizing a new device to a Telegram accounts simply consists of entering a verification code received by SMS when 2-step authentication is not enabled. At 3:08AM the attacker enters the authorization code and gets access to Oleg’s account. The Telegram login notification reveals that the attacker is using a &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/vysheng/tg&quot;&gt;Telegram command-line interface&lt;/a&gt; with an IP of a &lt;a href=&quot;https://atlas.torproject.org/#details/6C143720FFF8469EF6A5C5B4066366340CF6C0D1&quot;&gt;Tor exit node&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/img/tghack/telegram-hack-exit-node.png&quot; alt=&quot;The Tor Exit Node used to hack into Oleg&apos;s Telegram account.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Four minutes later, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/alburov/status/725939782191206402?lang=en&quot;&gt;the same Tor exit node IP address&lt;/a&gt;, logs into &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/alburov?lang=en&quot;&gt;George Alburov’s&lt;/a&gt; Telegram account. It is currently unknown if other accounts were breached that night. Messages logs (excluding Telegram Secret Chats) and contacts information were likely the information seeked by the attacker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because Oleg was sleeping during the attack, he only noticed the notification in the morning. He called MTS Customer Support, after consulting with the “expert department”, they told him that the security service was involved and that SMS was indeed disabled from 2:25 AM to 4:55 AM. Oleg’s request for talking to the security service was denied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sorm-russias-calea&quot;&gt;SORM, Russia’s CALEA&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the political activities of both targets, the most probable theory is that the attacker was a Russian governmental agency working in collaboration with MTS under the SORM law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SORM&quot;&gt;SORM&lt;/a&gt;, standing for Система Оперативно-Розыскных Мероприятий which translates to &lt;em&gt;System for Operative Investigative Activities&lt;/em&gt;, is Russia’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Communications_Assistance_for_Law_Enforcement_Act&quot;&gt;CALEA&lt;/a&gt;. SORM has been around since 1996 to enable wiretaps of telephone communications. It evolved over the years to allow broader access to electronic communications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If SMS interception capabilities exist, why would they go through the hassle of disconnecting the SMS service? One possible theory is that they hoped the intrusion would be unnoticed if the targets didn’t receive the text message. This would allow them to proceed to data exfiltration from the Telegram account without the risk of being shut down halfway through. The issue with this theory is that Telegram notifies you on your primary device when a new device is logged in. So despite not having seen the new activation SMS at the time, Oleg could have detected it instantly because of the Telegram notification. Additionally, attackers didn’t log themselves out, remaining visible after Oleg woke up in Telegram’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://telegram.org/blog/sessions-and-2-step-verification&quot;&gt;active sessions&lt;/a&gt;. So it remains unclear to me what the advantage was over a regular interception. If they hoped to be undetected, this was really sloppy and unprepared.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;phone-numbers-for-authentication&quot;&gt;Phone numbers for authentication&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most messaging apps and some 2-step authentication providers rely on phone numbers as an authentication factor. Why are so may services using identifiers that are assigned by mostly state-owned companies and that are subject to CALEA-like laws and awfully insecure (IMSI catchers/SS7) against nation state adversaries?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using phone number identifiers is a significant usability and growth advantage. You can leverage the social graph that people already have on their phone. After signup, they can instantly see who uses the service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also enables service providers to not have to store a buddy list unencrypted on servers since the social graphs are in the phone’s address book.
(Note: Some applications like Telegram store a copy of your address book unencrypted on their servers, not using that property.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it also turns out that it’s really convenient to rely on someone else key management infrastructure since usable authentication is a hard problem to solve. Most telcos have (insecure) processes to re-assign you your number when you lose your phone or if someone steals your SIM card keys. Those processes rely on providing some proof-of-identity. But that can be spoofed too. Last year, two investigative journalists at &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Novaya_Gazeta&quot;&gt;Novaya Gazeta&lt;/a&gt; were told that their SIM cards were reissued by unknown people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those processes clearly fall short. As we cannot solely rely on phone numbers to authenticate, Pavel Durov recommended &lt;em&gt;users from troubled countries&lt;/em&gt; to enable 2-step authentication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Users from troubled countries: make sure you have 2-step verification enabled – in Telegram and other services &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/w81h4PjFv4&quot;&gt;https://t.co/w81h4PjFv4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Pavel Durov (@durov) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/durov/status/726104566899609600&quot;&gt;April 29, 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that mitigation is a good first step, but insufficient, especially for people in troubled countries. An attacker might also suspect a user to have enabled 2-step authentication and therefore target some of his contacts to access the chat logs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such an attack is significantly mitigated, and deterred, by the adoption of end-to-end encryption. The detection of new devices can be cryptographically enforced and previous message history not accessible to an attacker capable of intercepting an SMS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the lesson from this might be something like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Always use end-to-end encryption. As the underlying authentication layer can be spoofed, verify fingerprints for important communications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 30 Apr 2016 08:30:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.fredericjacobs.com/blog/2016/04/30/more-on-sms-logins/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.fredericjacobs.com/blog/2016/04/30/more-on-sms-logins/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Double Ratchet &amp; the Quantum Computers</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The double ratchet &lt;a href=&quot;https://whispersystems.org/blog/signal-inside-and-out/&quot;&gt;was previously known&lt;/a&gt; as the Axolotl ratchet.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With recent developments in quantum information processing and computation, there has been a lot of chatter about moving to post-quantum cryptography. The &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2016/01/27/NSA-QC/&quot;&gt;NSA&lt;/a&gt; and NIST have already called for the standardization of post-quantum crypto and its swift adoption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Replacing some primitives is easier than others. Doubling symmetric key sizes suffices to counter the key space search speedup provided by Grover search which requires work proportional to the square root of the size of the key space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Replacing public-key systems appears to be a more challenging, requiring to move to new primitives who derive their hardness from entirely different problems. Most of those problems have been around for some time and the hardness from the general problem is reasonably well understood. But when it comes to &lt;a href=&quot;http://eprint.iacr.org/2016/351&quot;&gt;instantiating specific instances&lt;/a&gt; and working on side-channel resistant implementations, we’re still in infancy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other factors such as significantly longer &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Post-quantum_cryptography#Key_size_table&quot;&gt;key sizes&lt;/a&gt; are hindering adoption. Whether a trade-off is acceptable or not depends on the context. Hash-based signatures are a very elegant construction that could already be used when signature sizes are negligible compared to the size of the signed content such as software updates. &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/agl__&quot;&gt;Adam Langley&lt;/a&gt; wrote a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.imperialviolet.org/2013/07/18/hashsig.html&quot;&gt;brilliant post explaining how they work&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Algorithm&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Public key size (bits)     &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Private key size (bits)&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Ring-LWE&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;6595&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;14000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;NTRU&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;6130&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;6743&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Hash signature&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;36,000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;36,000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Goppa-based McEliece&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;8,373,911&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;92,027&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some mobile messaging apps are experimenting with post-quantum primitives such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://post-quantum.com/pqchat&quot;&gt;PQChat&lt;/a&gt; that is using McEliece for message encryption. While McEliece is a nice primitive, the PQChat message encryption protocol has not been independently studied and documented. End-to-end encryption protocols such as OTR or the double ratchet use ephemeral keys extensively to provide strong perfect forward secrecy. 8Mb public keys are making it hard to engineer any kind of protocol with similar forward secrecy features that would work well on mobile, knowing that the double ratchet sends a new ephemeral DH key with every message.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This led me to think about what protection the double ratchet actually provides against an adversary who can use a quantum computer to break the ratchet’s DH primitive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re not familiar with the double ratchet, the Open Whisper Systems blog has &lt;a href=&quot;https://whispersystems.org/blog/advanced-ratcheting/&quot;&gt;a very good post&lt;/a&gt; about it. As its name suggests, it combines two kinds of ratchets, namely a Diffie-Hellman ratchet and a hash-iterated one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ratchet is initialized with a &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;RootKey&lt;/code&gt; that is derived from a key exchange, in the case of Signal or WhatsApp, that is the &lt;a href=&quot;https://whispersystems.org/blog/simplifying-otr-deniability/&quot;&gt;3DH key exchange&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;MK      CK      RK      CK      MK
--      --      --      --      --
                |
                |
      PRF(RK, ECDH(A1,B0))
               /|
              / |
             /  - PRF(RK, ECDH(A1,B1))
     CK-A1-B0   |\
         |      | \
MK-0 ----+      |  \
         |      |   CK-A1-B1
MK-1 ----+      |       |
         |      |       +---- MK-0
MK-2 ----+      |       |
                |       +---- MK-1
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An important fact is that each new &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;RootKey&lt;/code&gt; is derived through a PRF from a previous &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;RootKey&lt;/code&gt; and the output of DH key agreement. The fact that it is derived, not only from a DH agreement, but also from a previous value is a valuable mitigation when we think about the threat posed by quantum computers. If the PRF used for the derivation is secure, then even if the adversary can break the ephemeral DH part, he won’t be able to recover the new &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;RootKey&lt;/code&gt; without the previous one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A consequence of that design, is that an adversary has to &lt;strong&gt;record every single message since the session initialization or he loses his capability to decrypt any subsequent messages&lt;/strong&gt; for future messages, even if he can continue to break the ephemeral DH. If the adversary didn’t intercept the 3DH key agreement, he would not be able to decrypt any subsequent messages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s a really cool property of the protocol. ZRTP has similar property if &lt;a href=&quot;http://zfoneproject.com/faq.html#keycontinuity&quot;&gt;key continuity&lt;/a&gt; is implemented (not the case in Signal) but most other protocols (MTProto, SSH, Threema …) do not have that feature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I do think it’s important to move to new primitives soon, cryptographic protocols can be used to mitigate the risk of anyone being able to break your public-key primitives by relying on well-proven symmetric key systems. Most people compare products solely on the primitives or key sizes, making abstractions of protocols and implementations, which are the global picture that truly matters.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 07 Apr 2016 15:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.fredericjacobs.com/blog/2016/04/07/qc-axolotl/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.fredericjacobs.com/blog/2016/04/07/qc-axolotl/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>My First TEDx Talk</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/img/tedx/meOnStage.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Me giving a talk at TEDx Brussels&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I gave a TEDx talk in Brussels on the 14th of March on the topic of master keys. Giving a TEDx talk is a very challenging and intimidating experience for anyone who is not an english native speaker since the bar is so high and most speakers have extensive public speaking experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;transcript&quot;&gt;Transcript&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last August, I was getting ready for a trip to the United States. After packing my luggage, I thought it would be useful to have a lock to protect some valuables in my luggage both while traveling and when I was hiking, leaving luggage behind. After a little bit of searching, I found my lock in the closet. It seemed the lock could be unlocked either by entering a digits combination or by opening it with a key. But I couldn’t remember where I left the key.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/img/tedx/lock.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;My Lock&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, it turned out, I didn’t have the key.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It wasn’t even given to me when I bought the lock.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After 9/11, the Travel Security Agency was created in the US to “protect the nation’s transportation system”. The TSA made two partnerships to develop locks that they could open to inspect luggage without having to break the locks. They would do this by adding a key slot that could only be opened by the TSA keys. These locks became mandatory when traveling to the United States and any other lock would just have to be destroyed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the measure was of good faith after a horrendous act of terrorism, the results were really disappointing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TSA agents cut these locks off despite having the keys in more than 3500 cases in 2011 alone. A report concluded that there was a lot of uncertainty about the efficiency of the measures after observing increased luggage theft of both valuable goods as well as dangerous ones such as guns. Such thefts have raised concerns by national security officials that the same access might allow bombs to be placed aboard aircraft. And things got worse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I was traveling, someone on the Internet figured out that the Washington Post had posted pictures of the locks online, almost a year before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/img/tedx/TSAKeys.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;TSA Keys&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From there, a range of events unravelled really quickly. Within 10 days, a group of lock-picking enthusiasts had modeled the keys in high resolution and used 3D printers to reproduce the set of keys. The model can now be downloaded from the code-sharing website &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Xyl2k/TSA-Travel-Sentry-master-keys&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt; and reproduced by anyone with a 3D printer, in minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever security I could have had from my lock was at that point completely gone. Of course, these locks aren’t very safe to begin with, but now not even lock picking skills are required to unlock them. Anyone can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While these locks were meant to make us safer, they turned into a security nightmare. Let me give you another example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/img/tedx/Yale1620.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Yale 1620&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This key, known to firefighters as the Yale 1620,  gives you full access to any elevator in New York City. That means you can lock down any elevator in any skyscraper in NYC. But it also unlocks all the subway emergency exits and entries to any construction site in the city. Firefighters and national security officials have been describing the key as the ultimate terrorism tool if it ends up in the wrong hands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last September, a reporter from the New York Post &lt;a href=&quot;http://nypost.com/2015/09/20/the-8-key-that-can-open-new-york-city-to-terrorists/&quot;&gt;revealed that the key could be acquired online&lt;/a&gt; for $8. I’m really not sure how people of New York City feel about realizing that they could be trapped at the top of a skyscraper or bombs could be placed in the subway tunnels by anyone willing to spend $8 on this key.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While both of these measures were trying to address very important issues, the way they were implemented ended up considerably weakening the security of these systems in general, instead of making them safer. The fundamental issue is the destruction of diversity which gives natural strength to the system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where previously a bad guy needed 300 million different keys to break into those locks, he now only needs to 3D print this set of keys. The TSA isn’t going to replace all 300 million locks that are unlockable with the keys that are available online. And New York City won’t be able to change hundreds of thousands of elevator locks overnight. While the city of New York is going to try and outlaw the ownership of those keys, about 50 people have already been arrested, thousands more will get a copy distributed as a file. The scale of these weaknesses make it so expensive and time-consuming to replace that about a decade will be needed to move away from those broken locks. And that is, if we get them to care enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a &lt;a href=&quot;https://theintercept.com/2015/09/17/tsa-doesnt-really-care-luggage-locks-hacked/&quot;&gt;recent piece in the Intercept&lt;/a&gt;, a TSA spokesperson reveals they don’t really care about the locks being compromised, citing them as being “peace of mind” devices, admitting that they never intended them to be safe anyways. Well, that’s reassuring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There has to be a solution, there has to. As the quote says:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“For every complex problem there is an answer that is clear, simple,”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and wrong …&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This universal key, sometimes referred as golden key is a perfect example of this. On paper, a master key that would allow the TSA to unlock luggage in the search for bombs sounds completely reasonable, but in practice the key will leak and everybody will end up being less safe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can give you a lot of other examples. I’m not a lock picker, but I do work with locks, digital ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/img/tedx/digitalLockpicker.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Digital Lockpicker&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I were to ask to anyone in the audience if I could take their  smartphone and post the content of it online, I doubt anyone would take me up on that offer. Whereas your luggage lock may only protect a few valuables, your phone’s passcode protects your thoughts, memories and most personal moments and information. Compromise of phone backups have been ruining careers and lives. Our phones have become an extension of our brains, an extension of the mind. They remind us about what we forget. They illustrate our memories with the pictures we take. They keep our most personal secrets. Realizing that the mental process can occur somewhere else than in the brain is something we need to start accepting as we’re increasingly connected and dependent on technology to make decisions on a daily basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/img/tedx/BrainPhone.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Brain Phone&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our phones are also our gateway to the Internet. It is often said that the Internet was not designed for the scale it has today since it was primarily designed to meet the needs of the ARPANET network that was connecting labs across the US. But, in the context of the ARPANET, thousands of miles of Internet cables were considered trusted. The Internet was not designed with security in mind. While many of the assumptions were reasonable for the ARPANET, the threat model has changed quite a lot. The Internet has been militarized and bad guys are running all sorts of hacking and sniffing operations on the Internet backbone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When email was invented, it was not designed with an adversarial threat model. In the email protocol, it’s trivial to send an email as someone else. Just google it, it will take you 5 minutes, or less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Email was not designed to be private either. A few weeks ago, I had to get paperwork filed with the Belgian Embassy. It turns out, that the email server of the diplomatic services worldwide doesn’t accept any mail over an encrypted connection. This means that anyone with network access between my email server and the Belgian Embassy email server can read my mail. This has to be fixed. Think about the consequences of this for a journalist or human rights worker in China or Iran.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/img/tedx/unencryptedMail.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Unencrypted mail&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to go the full distance. We can design messaging services that work the way users would expect, where messages are only readable by the sender and the receiver, and not by the creepy postman who has been reading your mail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/img/tedx/e2e.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;End-to-end&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The security community has been working on making a lot of these tools safer. And we’re getting there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The debate about backdoors is often framed in the press as being a debate between privacy and security. This is a false dichotomy. Privacy is the power of being able to selectively disclose your identity to others. You can’t have privacy without security. You can’t have privacy if you can’t technically enforce ownership on your data. Backdoors won’t make us safer either : introducing a master key in the system, as we’ve seen, weakens the security for everyone. Making us more vulnerable to theft and espionage, at scale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/img/tedx/power.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Call to action&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As companies and nations have been been failing to protect human rights such as privacy, we have been developing tools that protects those rights relying on the laws of nature, rather than the laws of nations. As these tools are making it into the mainstream, there is some push back against these technological advances from regulators and spying agencies who are unhappy about their job becoming harder. Now that the technology is mature, it is our duty to make sure that we can keep on using it to protect our rights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;video&quot;&gt;Video&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;360&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/9Duppgooa8Y?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Special thanks to Romain Ruetschi, Jessica Jacobs, Dylan Bourgeois, Nadim Kobeissi, Xavier Damman and Arnaud Benard for reading and providing feedback on previous versions of this transcript.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update (10th June 2016)&lt;/strong&gt; : Added video of the talk.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 16 Mar 2016 23:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.fredericjacobs.com/blog/2016/03/16/tedx/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.fredericjacobs.com/blog/2016/03/16/tedx/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Bumping into Stallman, again</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This is the second time I’m talking at the same conference as Richard Stallman, after the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ind.ie/archive/summit/&quot;&gt;Ind.ie Tech Summit&lt;/a&gt; in Brighton, this time was at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://fri-software-days.ch/index.php?lang=en&quot;&gt;Fri Software Days&lt;/a&gt; in Fribourg, Switzerland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One day before my presentation, I got an email from the organizers, letting me know that Stallman would like me to rename the title of my talk to remove any mentions of “Open Source Software” and replace them with “Free Software”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The email read like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Is it feasible to remove the terms “Open-Source” from the title of your presentation and replace them by “Free-libre software”? It’s the wish of M. Stallman, that will probably attend your talk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apparently, Stallman has been doing this for some time now, &lt;a href=&quot;http://pastebin.com/ADSHJrHm&quot;&gt;as this email from 2011 shows&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;So please make sure that all the publicity about the event (web site, email announcements, conference programs, direct mail, signs, etc), uses the term “free software”, not “open source”, when you refer to work that includes mine.  This includes to the title and descriptions of my speech, of the session it is in, of the track it is part of, and of the event itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I told the organizers, that I would stand by my use of OSS because that’s what was the right term to use in the context of my presentation on “(Open Source) Software Supply Chain Security”. My talk was about any kind of software that has accessible source code and referring to “Free Software” would have been restrictive of what I really wanted to talk about. Just to make it clear, despite Stallman’s wishes, no modifications to my title or abstract were made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Freedom starts with being able to choose the words I use to describe my own talk, if you ask me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/img/Stallman.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Stallman evangelizes Fri Software Days about Free Software&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Stallman narrative of blaming the users for choosing to use “what just works” and looks great over “Free Software” is counter-productive. Until you build beautiful and viable alternatives, you can’t keep on blaming the users. And standing in denial isn’t helping. In his call for action, he encouraged programmers and activists to join the movement but he systematically leaves out the people the “Free Software” community desperately needs the most, UX and UI designers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the Q&amp;amp;A, someone from the audience asked how someone could live from writing “Free software”. Stallman referred to himself as the perfect example that it was possible.    He finished answering that question with the following widely inappropriate comment:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-conversation=&quot;none&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;Ian Murdoch did kill himself, but he was more of an open source supporter. Free software didn&amp;#39;t kill anyone.&amp;quot; ~Stallman going too far ...&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Frederic Jacobs (@FredericJacobs) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/FredericJacobs/status/694235802100961281&quot;&gt;February 1, 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stallman is going too far, his religious war of “Free Software” against the evil “Open Source” is out-of-sync with reality, and has become quite embarrassing for anyone using GPL licenses and defend a different vision of the Free Software movement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update 1&lt;/strong&gt; (2015-02-03 15:00 GMT): Adding slides of the talk on OSS Supply Chain Security&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; class=&quot;speakerdeck-embed&quot; data-id=&quot;25823f7b79014e63955509834f1a4c80&quot; data-ratio=&quot;1.33333333333333&quot; src=&quot;//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 02 Feb 2016 23:25:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.fredericjacobs.com/blog/2016/02/02/stallmanism/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.fredericjacobs.com/blog/2016/02/02/stallmanism/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Revisiting the NSA Suite B Announcement</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In August 2015 the NSA &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nsa.gov/ia/programs/suiteb_cryptography/index.shtml&quot;&gt;released a major policy statement&lt;/a&gt; on the need for post-quantum cryptography, updating its Suite B recommendations in the process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The announcement surprised most of the crypto community with inconsistencies in the recommendations and interrogations about whether or not the threat posed by quantum computers was overblown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In their &lt;a href=&quot;https://eprint.iacr.org/2015/1018&quot;&gt;“A Riddle Wrapped in an Enigma”&lt;/a&gt; paper, N. Koblitz &amp;amp; Alfred Menezes speculated about NSA freaking out about the adoption of ECC. Matthew Green &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.cryptographyengineering.com/2015/10/a-riddle-wrapped-in-curve.html&quot;&gt;also critically blogged about the paper.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier this month, the IAD quietly &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.iad.gov/iad/library/ia-guidance/ia-solutions-for-classified/algorithm-guidance/cnsa-suite-and-quantum-computing-faq.cfm&quot;&gt;posted a FAQ&lt;/a&gt; document providing some more details about the changes in the recommendations. Here are some highlights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;compliance&quot;&gt;Compliance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fredericjacobs.com/blog/2015/12/18/COMSEC/&quot;&gt;NSA COMSEC Guide&lt;/a&gt; it was revealed that NSA was highly interested in collaborating with the industry so that industry could provide more “integrated” encryption solutions and NSA wouldn’t have to layer crypto on top of commercial products. Therefore, the FAQ document is mostly targeted for these “NSS” (national security systems) vendors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;timing&quot;&gt;Timing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The FAQ claims that the timing of the Suite B updates was an opportune moment to make the announcement about Quantum resistance but no particular breakthrough motivated the update of the recommendations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;primitives&quot;&gt;Primitives&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The current Suite B recommendations are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;RSA 3072-bit or larger&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;DH 3072-bit or larger&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ECDH and ECDSA with NIST P-384&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;SHA-384&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;AES-256&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;with the note:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;NSA prefers the use of ECDH with P-384 and 3072-bit DH for key establishment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the document explicitly says the following primitives should no longer be used for NSS:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ECDH and ECDSA with NIST P-256&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;SHA-256&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;AES-128&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;RSA with 2048-bit keys&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;DH with 2048-bit keys&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;threat-of-quantum-computing&quot;&gt;Threat of Quantum Computing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The document says that it takes up to 20 years for algorithms to be fully deployed on NSS, and the equipment is often used for 30 years or more. NSA refers to “many experts” that predict a quantum computer capable of effectively breaking public key crypto within that timeframe and that it is important to address that concern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Choosing the right time to champion the development of quantum resistant standards is based on 3 points: forecasts on the future development of a large quantum computer, maturity of quantum resistant algorithms, and an analysis of costs and benefits to NSS owners and stakeholders. NSA believes the time is now right—consistent advances in quantum computing are being made, there are many more proposals for potentially useful quantum resistant algorithms than were available 5 years ago, and the mandatory change to elliptic curves that would have been required in October 2015 presented an opportune time to make an announcement. NSA published the advisory memorandum to move to quantum resistant symmetric key options and to allow additional continued use of older public key options as a way to reduce modernization costs in the near term. In the longer term, NSA is looking to all NSS vendors and operators to implement standards-based, quantum resistant cryptography to protect their data and communications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;nsa-on-nist&quot;&gt;NSA on NIST&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;NSA will continue to support NIST in the standardization process and will also encourage work in the vendor and larger standards communities to help produce standards with broad support for deployment in NSS. NSA believes that NIST can lead a robust and transparent process for the standardization of publicly developed and vetted algorithms, and we encourage this process to begin soon. NSA believes that the external cryptographic community can develop quantum resistant algorithms and reach broad agreement for standardization within a few years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;does-the-fact-nsa-is-making-this-change-today-mean-a-quantum-computer-exists&quot;&gt;Does the fact NSA is making this change today mean a quantum computer exists?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;NSA does not know if or when a quantum computer of sufficient size to exploit public key cryptography will exist. The cryptographic systems that NSA produces, certifies, and supports often have very long life-cycles. NSA has to produce requirements today for systems that will be used for many decades in the future, and data protected by these systems will still require cryptographic protection for decades after these solutions are replaced. There is growing research in the area of quantum computing, and enough progress is being made that NSA must act now to protect NSS by encouraging the development and adoption of quantum resistant algorithms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;qkd&quot;&gt;QKD&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NSA briefly mentions QKD as a possible solution. I haven’t seen any QKD scheme myself that has the desired no-MITM property that it claims it has. Most schemes make the unreasonable assumption that there exists a public classic channel between Alice and Bob and that Eve would only mess with the qubits. This assumes that the classical channel is already authenticated so it doesn’t really solve the post-quantum crypto problem since they already have a secure communication channel (symmetric crypto is not believed to be vulnerable to QC if key sizes make a Grover search unfeasible).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NSA says they have no plans to use quantum cryptography, it wouldn’t be realistic to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;on-the-rsadh-recommendation&quot;&gt;On the RSA/DH recommendation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NSA wants to keep supporting these “legacy” algorithms because of cost effectiveness, suggesting that asking those vendors to move to ECC, only to move to a post-quantum algorithm in a few years would be a waste of effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NSA makes it clear that they still encourage vendors to move to ECC, but if the vendors can’t comply to the new advisory within a limited timeframe, they can just transition to the quantum resistant cryptography, whenever that comes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The document brings light to some of the questions the crypto community had been wondering about since the announcement. Not all recommendations are equal. Nuancing that some algorithms (DH &amp;amp; RSA) are now being transitioned towards “legacy” status but are still in the recommendation for giving vendors more time to transition is an important clarification.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe ECC isn’t going away anytime soon, especially for systems at scale. Some HTTPS reverse-proxies serve millions of users and the move to quantum resistant crypto would make that impractical due to increased key sizes. Therefore, suggesting that vendors can just bump RSA key size waiting for a post-quantum standard sounds unwise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s exciting to see more people looking at NTRU or McEliece and working on better implementations than the naive academic ones but there is still a long way to go before large scale deployments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Probably see you on a NIST, CFRG or PQCrypto mailing list to discuss this further!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 27 Jan 2016 21:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.fredericjacobs.com/blog/2016/01/27/NSA-QC/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.fredericjacobs.com/blog/2016/01/27/NSA-QC/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>On SMS logins: an example from Telegram in Iran</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Most mobile messaging apps these days use SMS as a login technique. It’s really convenient because it doesn’t require the user to remember yet another username or identifier and telcos are taking care of the identity management such as re-assigning the phone number to you if you lose your phone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SMS are trivial to intercept for your telecom provider. And in almost all countries, they are actively cooperating with the state to help intercept text messages and phone calls. But it’s not only your telecom provider, devices like IMSI catchers provide a cheap and efficient way of intercepting text messages for a local adversary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Applications such as Telegram messenger, not only allows a user to signup with an SMS, but also enables them to log in to see previous messages. The application stores your messages, content and contacts as they disclose in their &lt;a href=&quot;https://telegram.org/privacy&quot;&gt;privacy policy&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We store messages, photos, videos and documents from your cloud chats on our servers, so that you can access your data from any of your devices anytime and use our instant server search to quickly access your messages from waaay back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An attacker, that can intercept a single SMS is therefore capable of reading your messages from “waaay back”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Attacks like that are not just theoretical. Let’s take a recent example, Iran.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Telegram has gotten a huge amount of signups in Iran and &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/durov/status/687254676157378560&quot;&gt;according to Durov&lt;/a&gt;, its founder, Iranian users constitute up to 20% of their user base.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Telegram was getting some traction over the summer (June 2015), Iranian users started getting unsolicited login messages to sign into the Telegram website, which were believed to be related to a Telegram interception program operated by Iranian intelligence. Check the replies to this tweet:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;fa&quot; dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;کیا این پیام رو امروز از &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/%D8%AA%D9%84%DA%AF%D8%B1%D8%A7%D9%85?src=hash&quot;&gt;#تلگرام&lt;/a&gt; گرفتند؟&amp;#10;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/%D8%B1%DB%8C%D8%AA%D9%88%DB%8C%DB%8C%D8%AA?src=hash&quot;&gt;#ریتوییت&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#10;&amp;#10;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/%D8%A7%D8%B3%D9%BE%D9%85?src=hash&quot;&gt;#اسپم&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/%D8%A7%D9%85%D9%86%DB%8C%D8%AA?src=hash&quot;&gt;#امنیت&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/Iran?src=hash&quot;&gt;#Iran&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://t.co/xxEJBZbWSf&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/xxEJBZbWSf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Nariman (@NarimanGharib) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/NarimanGharib/status/612310940453892096&quot;&gt;June 20, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the past few months, there has been a lot of chatter about the relationship between Telegram and Iran. It is widely known that Iran blocks services that blinds their intelligence branches and that are unwilling to cooperate. Durov repeatedly came out claiming that they were not collaborating with Iran outside of blocking porn and jihadi channels (for public content), which they are doing worldwide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/persianbanoo&quot;&gt;@persianbanoo&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/SinaKK&quot;&gt;@SinaKK&lt;/a&gt; We shut down porn / ISIS channels based on the reports from users. &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/telegram&quot;&gt;@telegram&lt;/a&gt; never does political censorship.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Pavel Durov (@durov) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/durov/status/687315543448285184&quot;&gt;January 13, 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More recently, some popular Telegram channels promoting political poems or ideologies have been shut down. Iranian activists asked Durov about why those political channels were suspended.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Mr &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/durov&quot;&gt;@durov&lt;/a&gt; can you explain why you closed the PDKI channel in &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/telegram&quot;&gt;@telegram&lt;/a&gt;? :)&amp;#10;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/Censorship?src=hash&quot;&gt;#Censorship&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/Telegram?src=hash&quot;&gt;#Telegram&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/PDKI?src=hash&quot;&gt;#PDKI&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/Iran?src=hash&quot;&gt;#Iran&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/wvUrCes7fT&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/wvUrCes7fT&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Kevin Miston (@KevinMiston) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/KevinMiston/status/686537567051890688&quot;&gt;January 11, 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;fa&quot; dir=&quot;rtl&quot;&gt;یک روز از خواب پا میشی، می بینی رفتی به...&amp;#10;کانال تلگرامم حذف شد/ کردند؟! &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/C5KMj99jhg&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/C5KMj99jhg&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; فاطمه اختصاری (@fatemeekhtesari) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/fatemeekhtesari/status/686847201797103616&quot;&gt;January 12, 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After investigation, Telegram said that the channels were not suspended, but deleted by their owners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/KevinMiston&quot;&gt;@KevinMiston&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/durov&quot;&gt;@durov&lt;/a&gt; Investigation showed: The owner deleted his account on Jan 10, so all his channels became unavailable. Nothing blocked.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Telegram Messenger (@telegram) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/telegram/status/686656336059318273&quot;&gt;January 11, 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are probably just a few examples of hacked channels. &lt;em&gt;Unlike surveillance, censorship can be observed.&lt;/em&gt; It’s only because Iran started deleting popular channels that it became clear that they were hacking into Telegram accounts but how many activists got arrested over Telegram discussions that were intercepted? That is significantly more difficult to evaluate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Further investigation of some of the cases:IRI hacking into accounts,not censorship.Tnx &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/telegram&quot;&gt;@telegram&lt;/a&gt; 4 being responsive&amp;#10;&lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/QGk7picBcF&quot;&gt;https://t.co/QGk7picBcF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Reza Ghazinouri (@ghazinouri) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/ghazinouri/status/687399529918894080&quot;&gt;January 13, 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite good intentions, it’s becoming clearer that a good number of activists who trusted the application that branded itself as the “safest” messaging app are getting their account hacked and channels deleted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Countries like Iran tend to be blocking applications that blinds their intelligence as they get popular. Repeated claims by the authorities that they wouldn’t block Telegram should already have sounded suspicious. &lt;strong&gt;If a single SMS enables you to get access to a user’s account and data, you designed your system with a backdoor that any serious adversary can exploit.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;does-this-affect-only-telegram&quot;&gt;Does this affect only Telegram?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No, other services where you only need to send an SMS to log in are affected by this. But unlike Telegram, a lot of other messaging applications don’t store your messages and content server-side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a reminder for all users of messaging apps in risky environment, &lt;strong&gt;verify fingerprints&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SMS activation in most messaging apps can be compared to your server sign in for Jabber when using OTR. It is just your login to the message server, unless you verify fingerprints, you are still at risk of interception.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mitigations&quot;&gt;Mitigations:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://telegram.org/blog/sessions-and-2-step-verification&quot;&gt;Enable 2-Step authentication (and verify active sessions while you’re at it)&lt;/a&gt; and only use “secret chats”.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Or just move to an application that won’t store plaintext messages on their servers if you’re operating in such a risky environment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;note-on-two-factor-authentication&quot;&gt;Note on two-factor authentication&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of the weaknesses of the SMS protocol, it’s generally safer to setup two-factor authentication with a YubiKey or TOTP (such as Google Authenticator). Unfortunately, many services don’t let you opt-out of SMS fallback for second factor authentication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Disclosure: I have previously worked on encrypted messaging software.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update I:&lt;/strong&gt; Telegram clarified that one of the mentioned channels was deleted because of inactivity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/CDA&quot;&gt;@CDA&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Ammir&quot;&gt;@Ammir&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/KevinMiston&quot;&gt;@KevinMiston&lt;/a&gt; This channel got deleted because it was created by an inactive account that was set to self-destruct by its owner.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Pavel Durov (@durov) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/durov/status/687632744252354561&quot;&gt;January 14, 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is also important to note that some other accounts could also have been compromised by malware since some samples are looking for activation SMSes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update II:&lt;/strong&gt;  I &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2016/04/30/more-on-sms-logins/&quot;&gt;posted in April 2016 an update&lt;/a&gt; after new cases emerged in Russia and Iran.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 14 Jan 2016 14:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://www.fredericjacobs.com/blog/2016/01/14/sms-login/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.fredericjacobs.com/blog/2016/01/14/sms-login/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
